let's now start with lecture 4 which is about
process scheduling here you have the instructions
about which parts you should read in the main
textbook plus as always the extra facultative
readings when it comes to the objectives of
this lecture the idea is that we will go deeper
into processes threads and their scheduling
and execution of course we will look at different
types of systems namely batch system interactive
systems and real-time systems and let me say
right now that you can take entire dedicated
courses about real-time systems so I'm not
going to go too much into details here is
just an overview of them and then we will
also discuss challenges when it comes to scheduling
in relation with multiple processor / multicore
architectures and let's start with the introduction
we have discussed in the previous lecture
about the fact that we have processes which
can have a single thread or they can be multithreaded
and we said that the operating system is performing
a lot of context switches in which it basically
changes the thread that is being executed
from one to another thread these can be different
threads that belong to the same process this
of course implies that we are talking about
kernel threads of a multithreaded process
but they can also be threads that do not belong
to the same process they can be two threads
from two different processes one thread that
is started could actually run parts of the
operating system code and so on so the first
distinction we need to make when we talk about
scheduling it's about the type of processes
we have we have CPU-bound and I/O bound processes
and this is what is being shown in this figure
a CPU-bound process is a process that once
it gets access to the CPU so it goes into
the running state it is most likely going
to stay there for long periods of time because
it needs the CPU to perform/to run its instructions
if you think about a data analysis process
that is doing a lot of complicated operations
over data if you start to run that process
then most of the time will be spent by running
instructions at the CPU and sometimes this
process might request I/O let's say to read
some data from a file or to store some data
but those are events that do not occur frequently
most of the time is using the CPU to actually
run the analysis on the other hand we have
I/O bound processes these processes make a
heavy use of I/O requests system calls and
so on so what it means is that with good probability
when you start running such a process when
you decide to schedule such a process it will
not take a lot of time before the next instruction
run by such process will actually request
some kind of I/O don't let yourself be fooled
by the name here when we say I/O bound it
does not mean that it takes a lot of time
to do input or output operations it just means
that the frequency with which these processes
are requesting input or output is high so
if you schedule such a process there are good
chances that in a relatively short period
of time this process will actually launch
a system call because it needs I/O and that
means that the process will be moved into
the waiting state if we think about when the
operating system can actually take scheduling
decisions then we have different possibilities
here of course when you create a process since
you use a system call let's say fork for example
that is a point in time in which the operating
system has the power to take a decision should
I keep running the parent process or should
I run the child process similarly is when
you terminate a process that's a point in
which you give control to the operating system
and one of the things the operating system
can do is to decide what is the process I
will run next and then we have I/O requests
and I/O interrupts so all these four possible
moments at which the operating system can
take decisions about what to schedule we also
have elapsed time I'm going to discuss this
in a second they are about non-preemptive
scheduling if the operating system can only
use the first four options to take scheduling
decisions then we are talking about non-preemptive
scheduling it does not mean that processes
cannot be interrupted when these are the criteria
used to schedule processes (non pre-emptive
scheduling) but it means that if they get
interrupted is because one of these four conditions/situations
is happening on the other hand we have an
additional point in time to take scheduling
decisions which could be elapsed time so we
could create a system in which every 10 milliseconds
we wake up the operating system and we let
the operating system decide should we keep
running the process we are running now or
should we run a different process if we include
this option in our scheduling then we are
talking about pre-emptive scheduling in the
sense that the process can be pre-empted after
a certain period of time so the operating
system can actively decide the condition upon
which it will be preempted and say in 10 milliseconds
I will wake up again so that I can take my
next scheduling decision this is with elapsed
time otherwise we talk about non-preemptive
scheduling